<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Site for Courses]]></title><description><![CDATA[Site for Courses]]></description><link>https://www.nastysoulmusic.com/feed</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 04:41:27 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.nastysoulmusic.com/blog-feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title><![CDATA[The Journey]]></title><description><![CDATA[Building a Solo This is one of my favorite solos on Beat Tape 2.  It has all the classic Tom Misch licks, the tone, and it builds...]]></description><link>https://www.nastysoulmusic.com/post/the-journey</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6315680caf8f087282ebd776</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 03:07:56 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/c0716c_f09761a92cfd451587aad8d6314a12aa~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>hemphillmusic</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>Building a Solo</blockquote><p>This is one of my favorite solos on Beat Tape 2.  It has all the classic Tom Misch licks, the tone, and it builds beautifully.  If you've ever heard musicians talk about creating a story with a solo, Tom Misch creates the musical equivalent to Moby Dick. (is that supposed to be a written book? idk, I've never read it, but people talk about it)</p>

<p>He started off by ascending the D minor pentatonic scale, one note at a time matching the kick drum.  The space and time between the notes as it slowly and gradually ascends and gets higher creates this beautiful sense of raising dynamic.  Then right when he can't go any higher, the beat kicks in and he hits a lick.</p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/c0716c_f09761a92cfd451587aad8d6314a12aa~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure><blockquote>Blues Licks not Blues Scales</blockquote><p>Almost every guitar solo has a form of blues lick in it.  Blues guitar is practically the foundation of guitar in modern music.  But recognize, don't play the blues scale....I repeat, DO NOT play the blues scale.</p>

<p>I know what you're thinking, WTF dude? Why did you put a graph of the blues scale up there then?  It's just a basic reference point.  To play a scale is to play all the notes in ascending or descending order.  Blues is not a scale, but a library of phrases and licks.  Tom has a few moments where he plays so fairly basic blues licks, and it fits perfectly with the flow of his solo and other pentatonic licks he creates.</p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/c0716c_0d17bda9b667489989093cbf173b2c25~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure><blockquote>The Misch Sequence</blockquote><p>Did I just dub this new term that'll catch on? Eh, maybe lol.  So, if you've heard any Tom Misch solo, you've probably heard him do this.  </p>

<p>A sequence is when you play a scale following a specific pattern.  In this tune, he plays two different sequences.  </p>
<p>1) up 2 notes and back 1</p>
<p>2) up 1 note and back 2</p>

<p>You can follow this sequence with any scale and do many other sequences.  In this song he plays the sequence to the pentatonic scale.  </p>

<p>Scale sequences are common in the jazz world but also very common in the classical world.  So much of classical music is built on scale runs that often has some kind of continuous pattern.  So, sequences are a very music thing, but it can be tricky to make it musical in an improvisational setting because it can sound mechanical or uninspired if applied wrong.</p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/c0716c_dd08f7adafc04de0a3faaa7339eb0e47~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure><blockquote>THIS Pent Scale!</blockquote><p>Add a little bit of juice!  Pentatonic scale can get you sounded lyrical, the blues scale can give you some soul, but the Pentatonic scale with the 9 add to it can make you sound low key sophisticated.  </p>

<p>And there is this specific way that Misch approaches this scale frequently with this lick that he keeps coming back to.  In fact, in my video analysis of Tom Misch's phrasing </p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/AJfHElXozII" target="_blank" ><u>https://youtu.be/AJfHElXozII</u></a> </p>

<p>I highlighted this lick, as it seemed to be a recurring idea in all of his jam sessions.  And it's a cool idea, so bring that shit into your own playing too!</p>

<p>Check out all these licks at the end of this video here: https://www.patreon.com/posts/57123947</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Wander With Me]]></title><description><![CDATA[I transcribed every part in the first track off of Tom Misch's Beat Tape 2 album, Wander With Me.  You can learn quite a bit from...]]></description><link>https://www.nastysoulmusic.com/post/wander-with-me</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6315680caf8f087282ebd777</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 03:07:56 GMT</pubDate><dc:creator>hemphillmusic</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I transcribed every part in the first track off of Tom Misch's Beat Tape 2 album, Wander With Me.  You can learn quite a bit from analyzing just the ending and pick up some really cool tricks to make your chord progressions more interesting or spicing up a song you are performing. </p>
<blockquote>Play This Voicing with a Major 7 Chord</blockquote><p>You may know a variety of things you can play (chord moves and such) that can add to the major 7 chord.  But what you hear in this song, is Misch playing this m11 voicing that slides down to the major7.  </p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/c0716c_139dddee3ae0424da291a1cfba9e69e3~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure><p>Basically, find the relative minor of the major7 chord, and play the m11 voicing on the top 4 strings.</p><figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/c0716c_9ad1cb51bddd41a2ad7cf5b270176509~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_307,h_351,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure><p>This voicing, in root position, the low note on the D string is the root of the chord.  (redundant, I know, but repetition is great for learning!) </p>

<p>A little bit easier to start with finding a relative VI chord is to start with a more common key like G major, where the VI is Em.  Find the E on the D string and create that voicing.</p>





<blockquote>Juicier IVm Resolve</blockquote><p>If y'all are hip to that move (often used as an ending/cadence) where you land on the IV chord, and then play the IV minor, bringing this unexpected sweetness to your song - try these voicings to add some extra juice.  </p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/c0716c_84052881e4a14c959bdfd99ee3f3e529~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure><p>Most often played as a IV - IVm or maybe a IVmaj7 - IVm7 .... try starting with a major 9 chord and simply lowering the 3rd to a minor 3rd so you have this exotic m9 but also with that mystical major 7 still in the minor chord.  </p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/c0716c_0d8697a0a4c343fb8ee324e39812c1e5~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_303,h_346,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure><figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/c0716c_3bd738fcd1a147db876d34fad744a322~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_296,h_340,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure><blockquote>Passing Chord City!</blockquote><p>I don't know how else to put this in a simpler context other than - if you wanna drop a bunch of passing chords that sound sweet, try this!  There's certainly practical ways to use this movement, but its simply a direction of chords all going towards this one chord...</p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/c0716c_150b12430b7543a6a910598e8cc7833d~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure><p>The most important thing to see and understand about this group of chords is the last three chords (Vm9 - I13 - IVmaj7) are the same as a ii V I in the key of the IV chord.  So another perspective would be to look at these chords as resolving to a I chord which would be </p>
<pre><code><strong>Imaj7 - bIIIdim7 - IIIm9 - IIm9 - V13 - Imaj7</strong></code></pre><p>Except I wouldn't necessarily think of the bIIIdim7 like a bIII chord, that's just weird to me - I just see any diminished chord (generally) as a diminished chord resolving to X chord.  So that's simply a diminished chord resolving to the IIIm chord.</p>
<blockquote>Surprise Ending</blockquote><p>Hot damn, I love those surprise endings!  The most common approach is using the parallel minor key signature.  So, if we're in the key of C major, play chords from C minor.  </p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/c0716c_88cea32143d74644b23702b511622b89~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure><p>Usually, you would here a bVI - bVII - I progression at the end to give it a super bright sound that can be quite unexpected.  But in this example, borrow the bIIImaj9 chord from the parallel minor and make the bVII chord a major 7 (diatonically it would be a dominant 7).  Playing the bVII as a major 7 makes it much softer and sweeter.  Not as strong as a resolve, but sometimes you don't want a lot of tension to bring us back home!</p>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>